[Music]
hi I'm Bill Ackman I'm the CEO of
Pershing Square Capital Management and
I'm here today to talk to you about
everything you need to know about
finance and investing and I'm gonna get
it done in an hour and you'll be ready
to go so let's begin in order for you to
get a better sense of finance and some
of the basic terms associated with a
business and investing in a business I'm
gonna use the example of a lemonade
stand we're gonna go into business
together we're gonna open up lemonade
soon so the reason why I'm using an
example of a lemonade stand is a very
simple way to understand the basics of
the business how to understand how our
business works our business generates
profits what's involved in raising
capital to start a company what you do
when you're ready to decide to monetize
your investment or take some money off
the table you'll be able to understand
each of these concepts through the very
simple lens of a small startup business
like a lemonade stand
[Music]
we're gonna go into business together
we're gonna start a company and we're
gonna start a lemonade stand and no I
don't have any money today so I'm gonna
have to raise money from investors to
launch the business so how am I gonna do
that well I'm going to form a
corporation it's a little filing that
you make with the state and you've come
up with a name for your business will
call it Billy's lemonade stand and we're
gonna raise money from outside investors
we need a little money to get started so
we're going to start our business with a
thousand shares of stock we just made up
that number and we sell 500 shares more
for $1 each to an investor the investor
is gonna put up $500 we're gonna put up
the name and the idea we're gonna have a
thousand shares he's gonna have 500
shares he's gonna own a third of the
business for his $500 so what's our
business worth at the start well it's
worth $1,500
we have $500 in the bank plus $1,000
because I came up with the idea for the
company now we need a little more than
$500 so what am I gonna do I'm gonna
borrow some money and borrow from a
friend and he's gonna lend me $250 and
we're gonna pay him 10% interest a year
for that loan now why do we borrow money
instead of just selling more stock well
by borrowing money we keep more of the
stock for ourselves so if the business
is successful we're gonna end up with a
bigger percentage of the profits
so now we're gonna take a look at what
the business looks like on a piece of
paper we're gonna look at something
called a balance sheet balance sheet
tells you where the company stands what
your assets are what your liabilities
are and what your net worth or
shareholders equity is you take your
assets in this case we've raised five
hundred dollars in exchange for the five
hundred dollars the person who put up
the money only got 1/3 of the business
the other two-thirds is owned by us for
starting the company well that's a
thousand dollars of goodwill for the
business
we're borrowed two hundred fifty dollars
we're gonna owe twenty fifty dollars
it's a liability so we've got five
hundred dollars in cash from selling
stock two hundred and fifty dollars from
raising debt and we owe $250 loan and we
have a corporation that has and you'll
see on the chart shareholders equity of
fifteen hundred dollars so that's our
starting point now let's keep moving
what do we need to do to start our
company we need a lemonade stand that's
gonna cost us about three hundred
dollars that's called a fixed asset
unlike a lemon or sugar or water this is
something you like a building you buy
and you build it it wears out over time
but it's it's a fixed asset and then you
need some inventory what do you need to
make lemonade well you need sugar you
need water you need lemons you need cups
you need little containers and perhaps
some napkins and you need enough
supplies so let's say have 50 gallons of
lemonade in our of the start of our
business now 50 gallons gets us about
eight hundred cups of lemonade and we're
ready to begin let's take a new look at
the balance sheet so now we've spent
five hundred dollars we only have two
hundred fifty dollars left in the bank
but our fixed assets are now three
hundred dollars that's our lemonade
stand our inventory is two hundred
dollars those are the supplies and
things that lemons that we need to make
the lemonade goodwill hasn't changed at
a thousand so our total assets are
$1,750 we still owe $250 to the person
who lent us the money
surely the equity hasn't changed we
haven't made any money all we've done is
we've taken cash we've turned it into
other assets that we're going to need to
succeed in our lemonade stand business
[Music]
let's make some assumptions about how
the business is going to do over time
we're gonna soon we're going to sell
eight hundred cups eliminate a year
we're gonna assume that each cup we can
sell for a dollar and it's gonna cost us
about five hundred thirty dollars per
year to staff our lemonade stand so now
let's take a look at the income
statement so the income statement talks
about the profitability about the
revenues that the business generate what
the expenses are and what's left over
for the owner of the company so we've
got one lemonade stand
we're selling eight hundred cups of
lemonade and our stand charging a dollar
so we're generating about eight hundred
dollars a year in revenue and we're
spending two hundred dollars in
inventory there's a a line item here
called cogs that stands for cost of
goods sold
we have depreciation because our
lemonade stand gets a bit beat up over
time and it wears out over five years so
it depreciates over five years we've got
our labor expense - for people to
actually pour the lemonade and collect
the cash from customers and we have a
profit we have an e bit and that's
earnings before interest in taxes of ten
dollars it's kind of our pre-tax profit
for the business we didn't make very
much money because you take that pre-tax
profit of ten dollars and you compare it
to our revenues it's about a 1.3 percent
margin that's not a particularly high
profit now we've got to pay interest on
our debts and we have a loss of $15 and
then we don't have any taxes but at the
end of the day we still lose money
should we continue to invest in the
business we've lost money in the first
year is it time to give up well let's
think about it
let's make some projections about what
the company's gonna look like over the
next several years let's assume that we
take all the cash the business generates
and we're gonna use it to buy more
lemonade stand so we can grow let's
assume we're not gonna take any money
out of the company let's we're not gonna
pay a dividend we're gonna keep all the
money in the company and reinvest it as
we build our brand we can charge a
little more each year so we're gonna
raise our prices about a nickel five
cents more for each cup of lemonade each
year and then we're going to assume we
can sell 5% more cups per stand per year
so we've got a built in growth
assumptions so let's take a look at the
company take a look at this chart you'll
see in year one we started out with one
lemonade stand we add one a year and
then we buy your five we're up to seven
because we've got a big expansion plan
our price per cup goes up a nickel a
year and our revenue goes from eight
hundred dollars and starts to grow
fairly quickly and the growth comes from
increased prices four cups of lemonade
and it also comes from opening more
stands so by year five we have almost
$8,000 in revenue our costs are
relatively constant which is lemonade
and the sugar that's about seventeen
hundred two dollars we have depreciation
as the more and more stands start to
wear out over time we've got labor
expense but by year five the business
actually doing pretty well we went from
a 1.3 percent margin to a over a 28
percent markets the business is now up
to scale we're starting to cover some of
our costs we're growing we're still
paying $25 a year in interest for our
loan and we have a earnings before taxes
after interest of $2,300 by the end of
year five so we put five hundred dollars
into the business we borrow 250 and by
year five we're making a profit of
$2,300 that sounds pretty good now we
have to pay taxes to the government
that's about thirty five percent we
generate net income or another word for
profits of fifteen hundred dollars by
the fifth year and about a dollar a
share so if you think about this our
friend put up five hundred dollars to
buy five hundred shares of stock he paid
a dollar and after five years if our
business goes as we expect he's actual
making $1 a share in profit that sounds
like a pretty good peel let's look at
the cash flow statement so as the
business becomes more and more
profitable we generate more and more
cash and the cash builds up in the
company we go from $500 of cash in the
company to over $2,000 of cash over the
period the balance sheet you know again
the starting balance sheet had shoulders
equity of fourteen hundred ninety
dollars but as the business becomes more
profitable the profits add to the cash
they add to the assets of the company
our liabilities have not changed and the
business continues to build value over
times again by the end of year five
we've got four thousand dollars of
shareholder equity and that's almost
three times what it was we started now
is this a good business or a bad
business how do we think about whether
it's good or bad one thing to think
about is what kind of earnings are we
achieving compared to how much money
went into the company
[Music]
now this is a business that we valued at
$1500 when he started someone put up
$500 for a third of the company we give
it a $1,500 value but the Ender fear
your five it's earning 50 over $1500 in
earnings so that's a over a hundred
percent return on the money that we put
into the company that's actually quite a
high number
we've spent $2,100 in Capitol building
lemonade stands and we earn twenty three
hundred and thirty six dollars in year
five on the capital we invested that's
over a hundred percent return on capital
that's a very attractive turn earnings
have grown at a very rapid rate a
hundred and fifty five percent per annum
this is really a growth company and our
profitability is gone from 1.3 percent
to 28.6% by year five that sounds pretty
attractive and it is so let's look at
the person who put up the loan well that
person put up $250 and the business has
been profitable we've been able to pay
them their interest of 10% a year $25 a
year and they're happy because they put
up $250 they're getting a 10% return on
their loan and the business is worth
well more than $250 we've got more than
that in cash as a result they're in a
safe position but they've only made 10%
of their money now let's compare that
with the equity investor the person who
bought the stock in the company that
person earned $1 a share in year five
versus an investment of $1 a share so
he's earning over a hundred percent or
about a hundred percent return on his
investment versus only ten percent for
the lender so who who got the better
deal
well obviously the equity investor now
why do the equity investor why do they
have the right to earn so much more than
the lender the answer is they took more
risk if the business failed the lender
is entitled to the first 250 dollars of
value that comes from liquidating the
company so the if you sell off the
lemonade stands and you only get 250
dollars the lender gets back all their
money they're safe they got their 10%
return while the business was going they
got back their $250 but the equity
investor the person who bought the stock
is wiped out because they come after the
lender
so what's what's the difference between
debt and equity debt tends to be a safer
investment because you have a senior
claim on the assets of a company and it
comes in lots of different forms you've
heard of mortgage debt on a home that's
a secured loan secured by a house but
you could have mortgage debt on a
building for a company there's senior
debt there's junior debt there's
mezzanine debt there's convertible debt
bottom line it's all debt comes in
different orders of priority and a
company and your the rate you charge is
in you know is inversely related to your
security so the better the security and
the less risk the lower the interest
rate you're entitled to receive the more
junior the loan the higher the interest
rate you're entitled to receive but you
don't you can avoid the complexity all
you need to think about is debt comes
first
it's a safer alone but your your profit
opportunity is limited now the equity
also their varying forms or something
called preferred equity or preferred
stock there's common equity or common
stock and again stock and equity are
basically synonyms there are options but
really not worth talking about today the
important point is that equity gets
everything that's left over after the
debts paid off so it's called a residual
claim now the good thing about the
residual claim is the business grows in
value you don't own your oh your lenders
anymore
but all that value goes to the
stockholder so the question is why was
the lender willing to take only a 10%
return when the equity earned a much
higher rate of return and the answer is
when the business started there was no
way of knowing whether it would be
successful or not in the lender made a
bet that if the business failed well
they could sell off a lemonade stand you
know cost 300 dollars to make it that
would have some lemons and lemonade even
if they sold at a much lower price than
the dollar they originally projected the
lender felt pretty comfortable that they
get their money back whereas the
stockholder is really taking a risk they
were betting on the profitability of the
company and they're taking a risk that
if it failed they would lose their
entire investment so they were entitled
to get a higher return or that the
potential to have a higher return in the
event the business was successful
let's talk about risk you know a lot of
people talk about risk in the stock
market is the risk of stock prices
moving up and down every day we don't
think that's the risk that you should be
focused on the risk you should be
focused on is invest in a business what
are the chances that you're gonna lose
your money there's gonna be a permanent
loss when you're thinking about
investing your own money when you're
thinking about one investment versus
another don't worry so much about
whether the price things up and down a
lot in the short term what matters is
ultimately when you get your money back
will you earn a return on your
investment how do you think about risk
well one way to think about risk is to
compare your risks to other alternatives
so you can buy government bonds and
government bonds are considered today
the lowest risk form of investment and
the US Treasury issues 10-year
three-year five-year debt there's a
stated interest rate and today a 10-year
Treasury you earn about a three percent
return so you give your government
thousand dollars you get thirty dollars
in interest at the end of ten years you
get your thousand dollars back so that's
very very safe and that sort of provides
a floor now obviously you're gonna make
a loan you can lend money to the
government and earn three percent well
they're gonna lend money to a lemonade
stand you want to earn meaningfully more
so in this case the lender is charging a
10% rate of interest why ten percent
because they want to earn a nice fat
spread over what they can make lending
to the government because the start up
lemonade stand business is a higher risk
business equity investors sort of think
about things similarly so the higher the
valuation the more risky the business
the higher the rate of return the equity
investor is going to expect and the
lower the risk business the lower the
return the equity investor is going to
expect and equity investors don't get
interest the same way a lender does what
equity investors get is they get the
potential to receive dividends over the
life of a company
[Music]
let's talk about raising capital you
started this lemonade business on the
point of this was to make money in the
first place
business is doing very well yet I as a
as having started the business coming up
with a name and the concept hired all
the people I've made nothing all right
so the business is grown in value but
where's my money I need money to buy a
car for examples I want to buy a car for
$4,000 what are my choices what can I do
well we've taken all the cash the
businesses generated we reinvested in
the business now the good news is we've
taken all that money we've been able to
use it to buy more lemonade stands and
these lemonade stands are more and more
productive and it's grown the value of
the business faster and faster and my
alternatives could include well instead
of growing the business so quickly
instead of investing in more lemonade
stands I could simply pay dividends to
myself now the good news about that is I
get money along the way it's bad news
about that is the business wouldn't grow
as quickly you have a business as
profitable as this lemonade stand
company and we can earn you know
hundreds of dollars in each and you
stand it makes sense to keep investing
well how do I keep my business going and
growing taking advantage of the
opportunities but take some money off
the table how do I do that sell my
lemonade stand business you know I
started this one in New York maybe
there's someone in New Jersey who wants
to buy me consolidate my lemonade stand
company my problem with that is once I
sell it I can no longer participate in
the opportunity going forward I believe
in this business I think it's gonna be
very successful over time so that's one
alternative the other alternatives other
than selling up a hundred percent of the
business is to sell a piece of the
business now I can do that privately I
can find an investor who wants to buy a
private interest in the company and if
the business is working off I can sell
them a piece of the business and we can
be successful the other alternative is I
can take the business public an IPO the
abbreviation stands for an initial
public offering and its initial because
it's the first time a company's going
public going public means you're selling
stock to the broad general public as
opposed to finding one investor by an
interest in the company and it's an
offering because you're offering people
the opportunity to participate what's
interesting as an IPO doesn't make
someone rich all it really does is it
takes a business that they already own
and it sells a piece of it to the public
and it gets listed on an exchange when
you decide you want to take your
business public you're gonna have to
reveal a lot of information to the
public in order to attract investors to
participate and the Securities and
Exchange
they're gonna study this perspectives
very carefully you're gonna make sure
that you disclose all the various risks
associated with investing in the company
and you're also going to have an
opportunity to talk about the business
that's kind of an exciting time for you
because when you sell shares to the
public that's really in most cases the
way to get the optimally high price for
the company but you don't have to sell a
hundred percent of the business to the
public in fact typically you only sell a
small percentage you get to keep the
rest you get to keep control of the
company but you get to raise money in
the offering and you can use that money
to buy the car that we were talking
about before
now before you decide to go public or
even to sell it at all probably a good
idea to figure out what the business is
worth so let's talk about valuation or
how to value business one way to think
about the value of your business is to
compare it to other similar businesses
now the stock market is actually a
pretty interesting place to look the
stock market is a list of companies that
have sold shares to the public and you
can look in The New York Times or The
Wall Street Journal or online on Yahoo
Finance or Google or other sites and
look at stock prices for Coke for
McDonald's and what the stock prices
tell you is what the value of the
company is and how do you figure out the
value of the company well you look at
where the stock price is you count how
many shares are outstanding shares
outstanding will be listed in various
filings with the SEC you multiply the
shares outstanding times the stock price
that tells us the price you're paying
for the equity of the company so if you
go back to our example of our little
lemonade stand we have fifteen hundred
shares of stock outstanding we sold them
for a dollar
initially a one third of them to a
investor and the business initially had
a value of fifteen hundred dollars so
what is the business worth today well
one way to look at it let's look at
other lemonade stand companies let's
assume another other lemonade stand
companies have sold either in the
private market the public market or a
price of 10 times earnings or 10 times
profits that will give you a sense of
value so let's assume another lemonade
stand company is trading at 20 times
earnings in the stock market
well we earned $1 per share in year 5 we
put 20 multiple on that dollar the
business is worth according to the
comparable about $20 per share we've got
1,500 shares outstanding
multiplied 1500 times 20 now our
businesses worth $30,000 its we had a
company that started that fifteen
hundred five years later it's worth
thirty thousand dollars that's actually
quite good well how do we raise four
thousand dollars if that's the
appropriate value for our business well
if we sold 200 of our shares to under
our shares that are today now worth
twenty dollars a share we could raise
the four thousand dollars that we are
talking about now what what would that
do what would happen if we sold two of
our share two hundred of our shares in
the market well our interest in the
business would go down because we write
today we own 66 and two-thirds percent
or two thirds of the company a third is
owned by our private investors well if
we sold stock in the market if we sold
200 of the shares that we would own our
share our ownership would go from
sixty-seven percent to 53 percent so the
good news there is we still have control
of the business because in most public
companies owning a majority allows you
to control the business going forward
but because the company's now owned by
public shareholders you have to make
sure their interests are properly
represented so you have to have a board
of directors a group of individuals who
represent the interests of the
shareholders who have a duty to make
sure that their shareholders are treated
properly and you wouldn't have the same
degree of flexibility you had when you
were a private company because you have
other constituencies that you need to
think about now the benefit of the IPO
is the stock would now be liquid
there'll be a market where it would
trade in the public markets and then
over time if I wanted to sell more stock
I could do so or new investors wanted to
come in they could buy stock and our
stock would now be liquid make me feel
better about this business in terms of
my ability to at some point exit or if I
wanted to raise more money I could sell
stock fairly easily in the market
because each day you could look up the
price either on the web on New York
Times or otherwise and you can figure
out what your business is worth okay now
how does this matter to you now the
purpose of the example of our lemonade
stand is just going to give you a primer
on what companies are what they do how
they earn profits what the various
reports they provide to investors who
investors can figure out what they're
worth and the purpose of this lecture is
to give you a sense of some of the
things you need to think about when
you're thinking about investing perhaps
some of your own money whether you want
to invest in a lemonade stand whether
you want invest in a cup
the market let's assume at 22 you got a
pretty good job instead of spending your
money on you know gadgets or fancy
apartment or not so fancy apartment or
going out and drinking a fair amount you
put some money inside you start
investing money let's say you could save
$10,000 at 22 and you can earn a 10%
return on that money between now and
then time you retire what would you have
in 43 years the answer is you put aside
$10,000 you don't save another penny and
you invested it in your 10% of your
money each year you'd have six hundred
thousand dollars in your 43 and the
reason for that is well in year one your
$10,000 would become 11 your two year
$11,000 would grow by 10 percent and so
you'll be earning interest not just on
your original principle but you'd earn
interest on the interest you during the
previous year and that compounding
effect allows money to grow in an almost
exponential fashion now obviously if
ever more than 10% you can earn even
higher returns no that's if you put
$10,000 inside in 22 you have $600,000
in 43 years that's pretty good
what if you had to wait not until you
were 32 the problem there is a year 33
you'd only have two hundred and thirty
two thousand dollars maybe that's not
enough to retire so a key thing here is
if you're going to be an investor it's
really one of the most valuable assets
you have today as someone who's 18 or 19
years old is your youth you want to
start early that your money can grow
over time
and what if you get her and 15% give me
a better sense of how powerful
compounding is remember at 10% for 43
years you'd have $600,000 that's pretty
good but if you're in 15% you'd have
over 4 million now you're in a pretty
good position in and so obviously making
smart decisions about where you put your
money has a huge difference in what your
retirement assets are now obviously you
put aside more than $10,000 we could put
aside $10,000 each year then your your
your wealth would be you know quite
enormous now just for fun if you were
one of the world's great investors
Warren Buffett being a good example if
you could earn 20% per year for 43 years
you'd have 25 million dollars again the
original $10,000 investment would
increase by twenty-five hundred times
over that period of time just by earning
a 20% return Albert Einstein said the
most powerful force in the universe is
compound interest so key is start early
earn an attractive return and avoid
losing money and you're going to have a
very nice retirement
[Music]
okay now let's talk about the risk of
losing money now let's assume that in
order to try to get a 20% return you
took a lot of risk and it turns out that
every you know every 12 years you lost
half your money because you hit a bad
patch and the market you made dumb
decisions where you're twenty five
million dollars at 20% would now only be
worth a million eight in 43 years so a
key success factor here is not just
shooting for the fences try to get the
highest return it's avoiding significant
losses over the over the period okay so
as Warren Buffett says rule number one
in investing is never lose money rule
number two is never forget rule number
one so if you can avoid losses and earn
an attractive return over time you're
gonna have a lot of money in many if you
can stick at it for a long period of
time okay so how do you be a successful
investor now I'm assuming that you're
not gonna go into the business of
investing assuming that you're gonna be
a doctor or a lawyer you're gonna pursue
your passion but you're gonna have some
money they're gonna save over time and
I'm gonna give you my advice on the
topic it's not necessarily definitive
vice but it's what the advice I would
give my sister my grandmother on what
she should do if you were in the same
position I think that's probably the
right way to think about it so number
one how do you avoid losing money what
are good places to invest well my first
piece of advice is despite the story
about the lemonade stand I'd avoid
investing in lemonade stands I'd avoid
investing in start-up businesses where
the prospects are not very well known
because again you don't need to make a
hundred percent a year to have a fortune
you just need to invest at an attractive
return ten fifteen percent over a long
period of time your money grows very
significantly so how do you avoid the
riskiest investments I would my advice
would be to invest in public security
invest in listed companies companies
that trade in the stock market why
because those businesses are tend to be
more established they have to meet
certain hurdles before they go public
the stocks are liquid so you can change
your mind if you want to sell if you
invest in a private lemonade stand it's
hard to find someone to take you out of
that investment unless that business
becomes fabulously profitable that's a
piece of advice number one invest in
public companies number two
you want to invest in businesses that
you can understand what I mean by that
is there are lots of businesses that you
come in that you deal with in the course
of your day and your personal life
whether it's a retail store that you
know because you like shopping there or
it's a product your your your iPad or
that you know you think it's a great
product but you know you understand you
have to understand how the company makes
money the business is just too
complicated you don't understand how
they make money
even if they've had a great track record
I would avoid it a lot of people thought
Enron was an incredible business because
it appeared to have a good track record
but very few people understood how they
made money it was good to avoid it
another very important criteria is you
want to invest at a reasonable price it
could be a fabulous business that's done
very well over a long period of time but
if you pay too much for it you're not
gonna earn a very good return the last
bit is that you want to invest in a
business that you could theoretically
own forever the stock market were too
close for ten years you wouldn't be
unhappy what do I mean by that now again
if you're going to compound your money
if at a 10 or 15 percent return over a
forty three year period of time you
really want to business it you can own
forever you don't want to constantly
have to be shifting from one business to
the next and what of what are businesses
that you can own forever well the very
few that sort of meet that standard may
be a good example is coca-cola all right
what's good about coca-cola
is it's relatively easy business to
understand you understand how coke makes
money right they sell a formula syrup we
two bottlers and two retail
establishments and they make a profit
every time they serve a coca-cola people
going to drunk a lot of coca-cola for a
very long period of time the world's
population is growing they sell in
almost every country in the world and
each year people drink a little bit more
coca-cola so it's a pretty easy business
to understand and it's also a business
that I think it's unlikely to be
competed away as a result of technology
or some other new product right it's
been around long enough people have
grown used to the taste you know they
make parents give it to their children
and you can expect that'll be around a
long period of time I think that's one
good example another good example might
be at McDonald's you may not love
McDonald's hamburgers but it's a
business that it's been around for 50
years you understand how they make money
they open up these little build these
little boxes they rent them to the
franchisees they charge them royalties
in exchange for
the name and they sell hamburgers and
french fries and you know what people
have to eat it's relatively low-cost
food the quality is pretty good and
they're great and they continue to grow
every year so I think the consistent
message here is try to find a business
that you can understand that's not
particularly complicated that has a
successful long term track record that
makes an attractive profit and can grow
over time so what are the key things to
look for in a business as I say that
lasts forever we want a business that
sells a product or a service that people
need and that is somewhat unique and
they have a oil t2 this particular brand
or product and the people are willing to
pay a premium for that
and a good example it might be a candy
business while people are willing to buy
generic versions of many kind of food
products flour or sugar they don't need
to have the branded product when it
comes to candy people don't tend to like
the Walmart version of the Kmart version
they want the you know the Hershey
chocolate bar or the Cadbury chocolate
bar or the See's candy they want the the
brand and they're willing to pay a
premium for that and so that's I think a
key thing you want the product to be
unique you don't want it to be a
commodity that everyone else can sell
because when you sell a commodity anyone
can sell it and they can sell it at a at
a better price and it's very hard to
make a profit doing that if you're
investing for the long term you want to
invest in businesses that have very
little debt in our little example before
we talked about our lemonade stand
you know there's $250 worth of debt I
didn't put too much pressure on the
lemonade stand company but if it had
been a thousand dollars we hit a rough
patch the business could have got on a
business for failure to pay its debts
the shareholders could have been wiped
out so if you can find a company that
can earn an attractive profits it
doesn't have a lot of debt they generate
vastly more profits than they need to
pay the interest on their debt that's a
safe place to put your money over a long
period of time you want businesses that
have what people call barriers to entry
you want a business where hard for
someone tomorrow to set up a new company
to compete with you and put you out of
business I mean going back to the
coca-cola example Coca Cola has such a
strong market presence you know people
have come to expect when they go to a
restaurant they can ask for a Coke and
get a coke it's very hard for someone
else to break in and of course there's
Pepsi and there are other soda brands
perhaps she's been around a long time
coca-cola and Pepsi have continued to
exist side-by-side over long periods of
time so when you're thinking about
choosing a company make sure that they
sell a product or a service that's it's
hard for someone else to make a better
one that you'll switch to tomorrow
you also want businesses that are not
particularly sensitive to outside
factors so-called extrinsic factors that
you can't control so if a business will
be affected dramatically if the price of
particular commodity goes up or if
interest rates move up and down or if
currency prices change you want a
company that's fairly immune to what's
going on in the world and I'll use my
coca-cola example I mean if you think
about coca-cola it's a product that's
been around probably 120 years over that
period of time there's been multiple
world wars the development of nuclear
weapons all kinds of unfortunate events
and tragedies and so on and so forth but
each year the company pretty much makes
a little bit more money to made it
before and they're gonna be around and
you can be confident based on the
history that this is a business that's
going to be around almost regardless of
whether interest rates are at 14% when
the US dollar is you know not worth very
much or the price of Gold's up or down
those are the kind of companies you want
to invest in a long term businesses that
are extremely immune to the events that
are going on in the world another
criteria if you think back to our
lemonade stand company as we grew we had
to buy more and more lemonade stands
those lemonade stands only cost $300
each but imagine a business where every
time you grew you had to build a new
factory to produce more and more product
and those factories were really
expensive
well that company might generate a lot
of cash from the business but in order
to grow you're gonna have to just
reinvest more and more cash into the
business the best businesses are the
ones where it doesn't they don't require
a lot of capital to be reinvested in the
company they generated lots of cash that
you can use to pay dividends to your
shareholders or you can invest in new
high return attractive projects I guess
the last point I would make is there you
invest in public companies it's probably
safest to invest in businesses that are
not controlled controlled companies kind
of like our lemonade stand business that
we took public the problem with a
controlled company unless the
controlling shareholder is someone you
completely trusts unless there's someone
that has a great track record for taking
care of so-called minority investors
than non controlling shareholders you
can
risk with proposition to invest in that
business because you're at the whim of
the controlling shareholder and even if
the controlling shareholder today is
some of that you feel comfortable with
there's no assurance that in the future
they might sell control to someone else
it's not going to be as supportive of
the shareholders the business so it's
not that you just you can simply have a
profitable business and a business that
has has done well you have to make sure
that the management and the people that
control the business think about you as
an owner and I can protect your
interests so these are some of the key
criteria to think about now when are you
ready to start investing money my guess
is you're a student you probably have
student loans perhaps you even have some
credit card debt you're gonna graduate
you're gonna get a job so you don't want
to jump right in and while you have a
lot of debt outstanding start investing
the stock market stock market is a place
to invest when you've got a good you
have money you can put away and you
won't need for five years or maybe ten
years so if you're paying relatively
high interest rates on your credit cards
you definitely want to pay off your
credit cards first before you think
about investing in the stock market your
student loans are probably lower cost
and your credit cards but again here my
best advice would be you know once you
if your student loans are costing you
six or seven percent well if you pay
them off as if you earned a guaranteed
six or seven percent return and you're
just better off getting rid of your
credit card debt and even your student
loan debt before you commit a lot of
material amount of money to the to the
stock market even once you you paid off
your credit card debt or perhaps you're
paid down your student loans you want to
have enough money in the bank so that
even if you were to lose you lose your
job tomorrow you've got a good six
months maybe even 12 months of money set
aside
[Music]
let's talk a little bit about the
psychology of investing so we've talked
about some of the technical factors how
to think about what a business is worth
want to buy a business at a reasonable
price you want to buy a business that's
going to exist forever that has barriers
to entry where it's going to be
difficult for people to compete with you
but all those things are important and a
lot of investors follow those principles
the problem is that when they put them
into practice and there's a panic in the
world and the stock market is heading
down every day and they're watching the
value of their IRA or their investment
account decline the natural tendency is
sort of to do the opposite of what makes
sense to be a successful investor you
have to be able to avoid some natural
human tendencies to follow the herd the
stock market's going down every day your
natural tendency used to want to sell
when the stock market's actually going
up every day your natural tendencies
want to buy so in bubbles you probably
should be a seller in busts you should
probably be a buyer and you have to have
that kind of a discipline you have to
have a stomach to withstand the
volatility of the stock market key way
to have a stomach to withstand the
volatility stock market is to be secure
yourself you've got to feel comfortable
that you've got enough money in the bank
that you don't need what you have
invested unless for many years that's a
key factor number two you have to
recognize that the stock market the
short term is what we call a voting
machine it really represents the whims
of people in the short term stock prices
are affected by many things my events
going on in the world that really have
nothing to do with the value of certain
companies that your investments you've
got to just accept the fact that what
you own can go down meaning clean value
after you buy it that doesn't actually
mean you've made an investment mistake
just the nature of the volatility of the
stock market how do you get comfortable
don't just buy a stock because you like
the name of the company you do your own
research you get a good understanding
the business to make sure it's a
business that you understand make sure
the price you're paying is reasonable
relative to the earnings of the company
let's say this is just not for you I
don't want to invest by individual
stocks that just seems too risky I don't
have the time to do my own research what
are your alternatives well your
alternatives are to outsource your
investing to others you can hire a money
manager or you can hire a group of money
managers there are a couple of different
alternatives for a start-up investor the
most common alternative are mutual fund
companies so what's a mutual fund a
mutual fund is a I guess technically
it's a corporation but where you buy
stock in this corporation and the and
the manager selects a portfolio of
stocks so what they do is they pull
together capital money from a large
group of investors let's say they raise
a billion dollars and they take that
money and they invest in a diversified
collection of securities now the benefit
of this approach is that with a tiny
amount of money you know you can even
less than a thousand dollars you can buy
into a diversified portfolio managed by
a professional manager who's compensated
to do a good job for you investing in
the market so mutual funds are a good
potential area for investment the
problem is they're probably seven eight
thousand maybe ten thousand different
mutual funds and some are fantastic and
some are not particularly good you need
to do research to find a good mutual
fund manager in the same way that you
need to find individual stocks so it's
not just the easy thing of just invested
neutral funds so here are a few key
success factors in identifying a mutual
fund or or a money manager of any kind
to select number one you want someone
who has an investment strategy that
makes sense to you you understand what
they do and how they do it they're not
appealing to your insecurities by using
complicated words and expressions that
you don't understand if they can't
explain to you in two minutes what they
do and how they do it and why it makes
sense then it's a strategy you shouldn't
invest in number two this is not
necessary this order this is probably
should be number one as you want someone
with a reputation for integrity if again
if you're starting out you probably want
to invest in some of a mutual fund
that's sponsored by some of the larger
mutual fund complexes as opposed to a
tiny little mutual fund that's privately
but by a mutual fund company that you've
never heard of there's some Dennis
in the larger institutions you can be
more confident that they're not going to
steal your money you want someone an
approach where the investor invest money
on the basis of value I know it sounds
kind of kind of obvious but you know
value investing is has a very long-term
track record and now there are other
kinds of investing including technical
investing where people are betting on
stocks based on price movements but I
highly recommend against those kind of
approaches so you want someone who's
making investments where they're buying
companies based on their belief that the
prospects of the business will be good
and that the price paid relative to what
the business is worth represents a
significant discount you want to invest
with someone that as a long-term track
rep long term track record and I would
say five years is the absolute minimum
and ideally you want someone who's got
10 15 20 years of experience investing
in the markets because there's a lot
that you can learn being a long term
investor in the market you want someone
who has a consistent approach where they
haven't changed what they do materially
year by year that they have a stated
strategy that they've kept too thick and
thin that's enabled them to earn an
attractive return over their lifetime as
an investor what we see in some ways
most importantly you want someone who's
investing the substantial majority of
their own money alongside yours you want
someone whose interests are aligned with
yours if it's a mutual fund you want
them to have a lot of money in their own
mutual fund if it's a hedge fund which
is a privately sold
fun for investors who have higher net
worth you wants a manager who's
investing alongside you as well
[Music]
[Applause]
we started with a little lemonade stand
company and the purpose of that was to
give you some of the basics and how to
think about a business you know where
the profits come from what revenues are
what expenses are what a balance sheet
is what an income statement is how to
think about what a business is worth how
to think about what the difference
between a good business is versus a bad
business how dead I offer is generally
lower risk but lower return how equity
investors or investors who buy the stock
or the ownership of a business have the
potential to earn more or lose more we
use that as a back just as the basics to
get some of the vocabulary to think
about investing and we talked about
investing in the stock market we talked
about ways to think about how to select
investments how to deal with some of the
psychological issues of investing we
covered a fair amount of ground in a
relatively short period of time
[Music]
now I entitled the lecture everything
you need to know about finance and
investing in less than an hour well it
really isn't everything you need to know
it's really just an introduction and
hopefully I didn't mislead you and
induce you watch this for an hour but
there's a lot more that can be learned
and there's some wonderful books that
can teach you on the topic I think
what's interesting about investing
whether you choose this as a full-time
career or not if you're gonna be
successful in your career you're gonna
make some money and how you invest that
money doesn't make a big difference in
the quality of life that you have and
perhaps that your children have or the
kind of house you're able to buy or the
retirement that you're gonna be able to
enjoy and we talked about the difference
between a 10% return and a 15 and 20%
return over a very long lifetime what
impact that has in terms of how much
wealth you create over the period so
investing is gonna be important to you
whether you like it or not and learning
more about investing is gonna have a big
impact on your your your quality of life
if money is something that you need in
order to meet some of your goals I got
interested when I was probably 22 or 23
I started interested in being an
investor and I read a book I read book
called the intelligent investor was
written by Ben Graham and Ben Grimm is a
famous value investor and it's kind of
like reading jean-paul Sartre Zechs
essays and existentialism you read it
and it's either is an epiphany and it
affects the way you live your life where
it's of no interest to you and this was
the equivalent but in investing I found
it fascinating and what I'd like to
about investing is something very
accessible even to someone who's 22 or
23 what's kept me intrigued is that one
of the it's one of the few jobs where
every day you can study something new
you're constantly learning about new
businesses new situations new management
teams new issues so it's infinitely
challenging and the
in the stock market are obviously very
dynamic places so the challenges
continue these same concepts while
they're useful in deciding how to invest
your portfolio they're also very useful
to you in thinking about decisions like
buying a home making decisions in your
line of work whether to hire additional
people you know this these kinds of
calculations and thought processes are
are helpful and they're helpful in life
and I recommend that you learn more
thank you for paying attention and I
wish you well
[Music]